<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-06-28T16:59:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Shooting Companion</title><subtitle>Shooting blog by Tim Pope</subtitle><author><name>Tim Pope</name><email>tim@code-on-the-brain.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Preparing to shoot at 1200 Yards</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2017/06/22/preparing-ballistics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing to shoot at 1200 Yards" /><published>2017-06-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2017/06/22/preparing%20ballistics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2017/06/22/preparing-ballistics/">&lt;p&gt;Some Members of Christchurch Gun Club will soon be taking up the challenge of shooting at 1200 Yards - We’ve been shooting 1000 Yards for a while and decided we wanted to make things even more challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us will be using .308 calibre rifles and so this distance will be truly pushing the limits (at this range our bullets will likely have dropped through the transonic and into subsonic speeds before hopefully hitting somewhere on the paper) and so we need to check whether we have the scope adjustment needed and have a rough idea of the windage and elevation settings we’ll need on the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help our less nerdy members this post is going to be a guide to setting up a ballistic calculator, tweaking the settings so that the elevation readings match those of your scope, confirming you have the adjustment needed and then noting some useful information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ballistics involves a lot of variables (bullet weight, velocity, coefficient etc) fortunately most long-range shooters will know most of these, but there’s a good chance that you might not have measured your scope height (unless you’ve previously used a ballistic calculator) so go read my quick howto here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are also going to want to dig out any details you have on your velocity and scope settings at this point :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ballistic calculator I’m going to use for this is JBM Ballistics (http://www.jbmballistics.com/cgi-bin/jbmtraj_drift-5.1.cgi)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s dive right in and start inputting values&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off you need to select your bullet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm1.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The library is pretty extensive - so you should just be able to select it in the dropdown and ignore all these other values (they’ll be ignored when you click calculate) - If there is a ‘Litz’ option for your bullet use it’
(If you are using a plastic tipped bullet and you want to be nosey about its stability factor you can add this here if you wish)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up we need to set our muzzle velocity… you do know it right? (if you don’t, take a best guess as we’ll be altering this anyway)
Also set your sight height and barrel twist in this section&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm2.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kill the wind and target speed - you can play with these later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm3.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set your Max range up to 1300 (I always prefer to see an extra row of data than I need), If you knopw your scopes true 0 range then set it here (otherwise we’ll be returning to this anyway)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm4.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for enviromentals we’re going to take a guess for the moment (as that’ll be good enough for now) but really these should be set to the values you’re shooting in - FYI the altitude for Bisley is about 200ft above sea-level&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm5.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now depending on what measurement your scope uses (MOA , Mil , cm/100m) you may need to change the column 2 units&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm6.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tick ‘mark sound barrier crossing’ - this is useful to see where you’re starting to run out of steam&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm7.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now hit calculate and you’ll get the ‘table of doom’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/jbm8.png&quot; alt=&quot;JBM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data is useful… By looking at the 3rd column (drop) I can say that I’ll need an additional 13.2 MOA elevation on top of my 1000 yard scope setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My raw scope setting for the 1000 is 21.5 so with the the above I’d need to set the scope to 34.7 MOA… Now here’s an impotant note: &lt;strong&gt;My scope has an elevation range of 70 MOA (so 35 up and 35 down)… so you can see I am really pushing that limit…. But don’t panic Mr Mannering as the reticle has another 20 MOA of markings available for me to use.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is something that’s important for you to check yourselves.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tim Pope</name><email>tim@code-on-the-brain.com</email></author><summary type="html">Some Members of Christchurch Gun Club will soon be taking up the challenge of shooting at 1200 Yards - We’ve been shooting 1000 Yards for a while and decided we wanted to make things even more challenging.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Measuring sight height</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2017/06/21/sight-height/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Measuring sight height" /><published>2017-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2017/06/21/sight%20height</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2017/06/21/sight-height/">&lt;p&gt;One major rule with External ballistics is that if you input rubbish values - you’re going to get rubbish values back out again&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important but often overlooked value where this is true is ‘sight height’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s a quick guide on how to measure it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locate calipers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measure diameter of scope - then halve it to get the radius
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/scope_dia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scope&quot; /&gt;
  So here my scope diameter is 65.14mm and so halved is 32.57mm&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measure diameter of barrel (be sure to measure barrel width in line with where you measure scope width as barrels are often tapered) - halve this to get the radius
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/barrel_dia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scope&quot; /&gt;
  My barrel diameter is 27.7mm and so the radius is 13.85mm&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measure the distance between the barrel and the scope
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://www.shootingcompanion.com/images/scope_barrel_space.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scope&quot; /&gt;
  The distance between the two for me is 2.43mm&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally add the gap distance to the scope radius and the barrel radius - Which gives you the distance between the centre of the barrel to the centre of the scope.
  So for me 32.57 + 13.85 + 2.43 = 48.85mm which is 1.92in&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write that number down - it’ll be handy in future!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Tim Pope</name><email>tim@code-on-the-brain.com</email></author><summary type="html">One major rule with External ballistics is that if you input rubbish values - you’re going to get rubbish values back out again</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2017/01/05/introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Post" /><published>2017-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2017/01/05/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2017/01/05/introduction/">&lt;p&gt;So after owning this domain for over a year and a half I’ve finally got around to actually having it go somewhere on the internet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the more technically interested this blog is built using Jekyll (https://jekyllrb.com/) and is hosted for free (yay!) using Github Pages (https://pages.github.com/) giving me a very simple and more nerdy way to keep a blog than I’d have typically done with something like wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not sure what you should expect from this site at the moment to be honest as previous attempts at blogging have always resulted in failure. But my current line of thinking is that it’ll have the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;*	The CGC F-Class competition scores - I maintain these as a spreadsheet on 
	Google Docs so it makes sense to embed these here (as I could not do this in our club forum)
*	I'd like to actually make some progress on my app and hopefully post some progress updates along the way
*	Some posts on load developments or anything I'm trying to 'up my game'
*	Any other inane ramblings that have anything remotely related to shooting
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Tim Pope</name><email>tim@code-on-the-brain.com</email></author><summary type="html">So after owning this domain for over a year and a half I’ve finally got around to actually having it go somewhere on the internet!</summary></entry></feed>